<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
	<title>Overview</title>
	
	<para>
		The user interface is devided into a tool bar and the actual board. At
		the main window lower end a status bar shows information about the status
		of the game. (see 
		<xref linkend="fig.program_overview" />
		)
	</para>
	
	<figure xml:id="fig.program_overview">
		<title>FreeNono overview</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="./images/programm_overview.png"
					scalefit="1" width="100%" contentdepth="100%" />
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>
				</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<orderedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Choose new nonogram: Choose a new nonogram to play. The
				currently running game will be stopped!
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Restart current game: Currently running or last finished game
				will be restarted.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Pause running game: Pause or resume the currently running
				game.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Stop running game: Stop currently running game and count it as
				lost.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Options: Calls options dialog to set preferences. E.g. the
				game mode can be set or keys can be assigned.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Show statistics (not yet implemented)</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Help: Shows a help dialog with information about playing
				FreeNono.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Nonogram editor (per default not active): With the nonogram
				editor you can create your own nonograms. Per default the editor is
				not active but will be available in the following versions. The
				created nonograms can be shared with other players.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Info: Shows information about authors and program
				version.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Quit FreeNono: Quit FreeNono when user do not want to play
				anymore.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Status field: Shows informations about the currently running
				game. If set as preference the name of the current nonogram is shown
				as well as the game mode and associated data like remaining game
				time or errors left. These information depend on the chosen game
				mode of the running game.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Game board: In the game board the player can fill the nonogram
				according to the given hints in the margins. Large nonograms can be
				scrolled via keyboard or mouse. A preview helps to get an overview
				of the board when playing these large nonograms.
			</para>
			<para>The margin numbers that help solve the nonogram as well as the
				current active field are visually marked. With mouse or keyboard
				fields can be marked as belonging to the picture. To assist the
				player fields can also be marked with an X to show that it is not
				part of the picture. When all fields of the nonogram are correctly
				marked the game is won.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</orderedlist>
</chapter>
