<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

	<title>
		Solution techniques
		<footnote id="wiki1">
			<para>Source Wikipedia: Nonogram.
				http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonogram#Solution_techniques</para>
		</footnote>
	</title>
	<para>
		To solve a puzzle, one needs to determine which cells will be
		boxes and which will be empty. Determining which cells are to be left
		empty (called spaces) is as important as determining which to fill
		(called boxes). Later in the solving process, the spaces help
		determine where a clue (continuing block of boxes and a number in the
		legend) may spread. Solvers usually use a dot or a cross to mark cells
		they are certain are spaces.
	</para>
	<para>
		It is also important never to guess. Only cells that can be
		determined
		by logic should be filled. If guessing, a single error can
		spread over
		the entire field and completely ruin the solution. It
		usually comes to
		the surface only after a while, when it is very
		difficult to correct
		the puzzle. Usually, only advanced and experienced
		solvers are able to
		fix it completely and finish such ruined puzzles.
	</para>
	<para>
		The hidden picture plays no part in the solving process. Even if
		it is
		obvious from the picture that a cell will be a box, it is usually
		treacherous to rely on it. The picture, however, may help find and
		eliminate an error.
	</para>
	<para>
		Simpler puzzles can usually be solved by a reasoning on a single
		row only (or a single column) at each given time, to determine as many
		boxes and spaces on that row as possible. Then trying another row (or
		column), until there are rows that contain undetermined cells.
	</para>
	<para>
		Some more difficult puzzles may also require several types of
		"what if?" reasoning that include more than one row (or column). This
		works on searching for contradictions: When a cell cannot be a box,
		because some other cell would produce an error, it will definitely be
		a space. And vice versa. Advanced solvers are sometimes able to search
		even deeper than into the first "what if?" reasoning. It takes,
		however, a lot of time to get some progress.
	</para>
	<sect1>
		<title>Simple boxes</title>
		<para>
			At the beginning of the solution a simple method can be used
			to
			determine as many boxes as possible. This method uses
			conjunctions of
			possible places for each block of boxes. For
			example, in a row of ten
			cells with only one clue of 8, the
			bound block consisting of 8 boxes
			could spread from

			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					the right border, leaving two spaces to the left;
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					the left border, leaving two spaces to the right;
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					or somewhere in between.
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			As a result, the block must spread through the six
			centermost
			cells in the row.
		</para>
		<para>
			The same of course applies when there are more clues in the
			row.
			For example, in a row of ten cells with clues of 4 and
			3, the bound
			blocks of boxes could be
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				crowded to the left, one next to the other, leaving two
				spaces
				to the right;
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				crowded to the right, one just next to the other,
				leaving
				two spaces to the left;
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				or somewhere between.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Consequently, the first block of four boxes definitely includes
			the third and fourth cells, while the second block of three boxes
			definitely includes the eighth cell. Boxes can therefore be placed in
			the third, fourth and eighth cells. Important note: When determining
			boxes in this way, boxes can be placed in cells only when the same
			block overlaps; in this example, although two blocks overlap in the
			sixth cell, they are different blocks, and so it cannot yet be said
			whether or not the sixth cell will contain a box.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Simple spaces</title>
		<para>
			This method consists of determining spaces by searching for
			cells that are out of range of any possible blocks of boxes.
			For
			example, considering a row of ten cells with boxes in
			the fourth and
			ninth cell and with clues of 3 and 1, the
			block bound to the clue 3
			will spread through the fourth
			cell and clue 1 will be at the ninth
			cell.
		</para>
		<para>
			First, the clue 1 is complete and there will be a space at
			each
			side of the bound block.
		</para>
		<para>
			Second, the clue 3 can only spread somewhere between the
			second
			cell and the sixth cell, because it always has to
			include the fourth
			cell; however, this may leave cells that
			may not be boxes in any case,
			i.e. the first and the
			seventh.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note: In this example all blocks are accounted for; this is
			not
			always the case. The player must be careful for there
			may be clues or
			blocks that are not bound to each other yet.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Forcing</title>
		<para>
			In this method, the significance of the spaces will be
			shown. A
			space placed somewhere in the middle of an
			uncompleted row may force a
			large block to one side or the
			other. Also, a gap that is too small
			for any possible block
			may be filled with spaces.
		</para>
		<para>
			For example, considering a row of ten cells with spaces in
			the
			fifth and seventh cells and with clues of 3 and 2:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				the clue of 3
				would be forced to the left, because it could
				not fit anywhere
				else.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				the empty gap on the sixth cell is too small to
				accommodate
				clues like 2 or 3 and may be filled with spaces.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				finally, the clue of 2 will spread through the ninth cell
				according to method Simple Boxes above.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Glue</title>
		<para>
			Sometimes, there is a box near the border that is not
			farther
			from the border than the length of the first clue.
			In this case, the
			first clue will spread through that box
			and will be forced outward
			from the border.
		</para>
		<para>
			For example, considering a row of ten cells with a box in
			the
			third cell and with a clue of 5, the clue of 5 will
			spread through the
			third cell and will continue to the fifth
			cell because of the border.
		</para>
		<para>
			Note: This method may also work in the middle of a row,
			further
			away from the borders. A space may act as a border,
			if the first clue
			is forced to the right of that space. The
			first clue may also be
			preceded by some other clues, if all
			the clues are already bound to
			the left of the forcing
			space.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Joining and splitting</title>
		<para>
			Boxes closer to each other may be sometimes joined together
			into
			one block or split by a space into several blocks. When
			there are two
			blocks with an empty cell between, this cell
			will be:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				A space if joining the two blocks by a box would produce a
				too
				large block
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				A box if splitting the two blocks by a space would
				produce a
				too small block that does not have enough free cells
				remaining
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			For example, considering a row of fifteen cells with boxes in
			the third, fourth, sixth, seventh, eleventh and thirteenth cell and
			with clues of 5, 2 and 2:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				The clue of 5 will join the first two blocks by a box into
				one large block, because a space would produce a block of only 4
				boxes that is not enough there. large block
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				The clues of 2 will split the last two blocks by a space,
				because a box would produce a block of 3 continuous boxes, which is
				not allowed there.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		<para>
			Note: The illustration picture also shows how the clues of 2 are
			further completed. This is, however, not part of the Joining and
			splitting technique, but the Glue technique described above.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Punctuating</title>
		<para>
			To solve the puzzle, it is usually also very important to
			enclose each bound or completed block of boxes immediately by
			separating spaces as described in Simple spaces method. Precise
			punctuating usually leads to more Forcing and may be vital for
			finishing the puzzle. Note: The examples above did not do that only
			to remain simple.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Mercury</title>
		<para>
			Mercury is a special case of Simple spaces technique. Its name
			comes from the way mercury pulls back from the sides of a container.
		</para>
		<para>
			If there is a box in a row that is in the same distance from the
			border as the length of the first clue, the first cell will be a
			space. This is because the first clue would not fit to the left of
			the box. It will have to spread through that box, leaving the first
			cell behind. Furthermore, when the box is actually a block of more
			boxes to the right, there will be more spaces at the beginning of the
			row, determined by using this method several times.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Contradictions</title>
		<para>
			Some more difficult puzzles may also require advanced
			reasoning.
			When all simple methods above are exhausted,
			searching for
			contradictions may help. It is wise to use a
			pencil (or other color)
			for that to facilitate corrections.
			The procedure includes:
		</para>
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				Trying an empty cell to be a box (or then a space).
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Using all available methods to solve as much as possible.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				If an error is found, the tried cell will not be a box for
				sure. It will be a space (or a box, if space was
				tried).
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		<para>
			In this example a box is tried in the first row, which leads to
			a space at the beginning of that row. The space then forces a box in
			the first column, which glues to a block of three boxes in the fourth
			row. However, that is wrong because the third column does not allow
			any boxes there, which leads to a conclusion that the tried cell must
			not be a box, so it must be a space.
		</para>
		<para>
			The problem of this method is that there is no quick way to tell
			which empty cell to try first. Usually only a few cells lead to any
			progress, and the other cells lead to dead ends. Most worthy cells to
			start with may be:
		</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				cells that have many non-empty neighbors;
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				cells that are close to the borders or close to the blocks
				of spaces;
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				cells that are within rows that consist of more non-empty
				cells.
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Deeper recursion</title>
		<para>
			Some puzzles may require to go deeper with searching for the
			contradictions. This is, however, not possible simply by a pen and
			pencil, because of the many possibilities that must be searched. This
			method is practical for a computer to use.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Multiple rows</title>
		<para>
			In some cases, reasoning over a set of rows may also lead to the
			next step of the solution even without contradictions and deeper
			recursion. However, finding such sets is usually as difficult as
			finding contradictions.
		</para>

	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Multiple solutions</title>
		<para>
			There are puzzles that have several feasible solutions (one such
			is a picture of a simple chess board). In these puzzles, all
			solutions are correct by the definition, but not all must give a
			reasonable picture.
		</para>
	</sect1>

</chapter>
