<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

	<title>Options</title>

	<para>
		FreeNono supports some game modes that make the game more fun to play.
		The game mode can be chosen in the options dialog (
		<xref linkend="fig.options_dialog" />
		).
	</para>

	<itemizedlist>
		<listitem>
			<para>Penalty: A maximum time is given. Each error results in a time
				penalty. When the time is up the game is lost. This mode is inspired
				by the genius "Mario’s Picross" of Nintendo.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Maximum time: In this mode only the time is relevant. You can
				make as much errors as you like. But be aware: cheating takes the
				fun out of the game.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Maximum failures: For all players who take the time to think
				carefully. Only the number of errors counts.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Count time: To get a high score in this mode the nonogram has
				to be solved in as little time as possible. Errors add some time on
				the clock.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Quiz mode: In quiz mode each error will be punished with a quiz
				question. When the question is answered correctly the game
				continues.
				If not the game is lost. Currently the questions are
				multiplication questions. The number range is between 1 and 10 for
				the first questions. Later the numbers range from 10 to 20.
				We are
				thankful for ideas about new types of quizzes. Please send
				ideas to
				<email>info@freenono.org</email>
				.
			</para>
		</listitem>
		<listitem>
			<para>Pen and paper: For all who like to solve nonograms on paper.
				The nonogram can be marked without rules. To win the game, each and
				every field has to be correctly marked.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</itemizedlist>

	<figure xml:id="fig.options_dialog">
		<title>Options</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="./images/options_dialog.png" scalefit="1"
					width="75%" contentdepth="100%" />
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>
				</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>Aside from the game modes more options can be set in this dialog.
		E.g. if the game board should be shown while game is paused or if
		wrongly marked fields should automatically be filled with an X.
	</para>
	
	<important>
		All options in the tab "game" will not be used until a new nonogram is 
		chosen or the current nonogram is started again.
		For a change of the program language the program has to be restarted.
	</important>

</chapter>
