<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter xml:base="../" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">

	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para>
	FreeNono is an open-source implementation of the japanese Nonogram
	game — a logic puzzle in which cells in a grid have to be colored or
	left blank according to numbers given at the side of the grid to
	reveal a hidden picture.
	</para>

	<blockquote>

		<attribution>Wikipedia: Nonogramme.
			Online: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nonogram.
		</attribution>

		<para>
			"Nonograms are picture logic puzzles in which cells in a grid must be
			colored or left blank according to numbers at the side of the grid to
			reveal a hidden picture. In this puzzle type, the numbers are a form of
			discrete tomography that measures how many unbroken lines of
			filled-in
			squares there are in any given row or column. For example, a clue of "4
			8 3" would mean there are sets of four, eight, and three filled
			squares, in that order, with at least one blank square between
			successive groups.
		</para>
		<para>
			These puzzles are often black and white, describing a binary image, but
			they
			can also be colored. If colored, the number clues are also colored to
			indicate the color of the squares. Two differently colored numbers
			may
			have a space in between them. For example, a black four followed by a
			red two could mean four black boxes, some empty spaces, and two red
			boxes, or it could simply mean four black boxes followed immediately
			by
			two red ones.
		</para>
		<para>
			In 1987, Non Ishida, a Japanese graphics editor, won a competition in
			Tokyo by designing grid pictures using skyscraper lights that were
			turned on or off. Coincidentally, a professional Japanese puzzler
			named
			Tetsuya Nishio invented the same puzzles.
		</para>
		<para>
			Non Ishida published three picture grid puzzles in 1988 in Japan under
			the
			name of "Window Art Puzzles". Subsequently in 1990, James Dalgety in
			the UK invented the name Nonograms after Non Ishida, and The Sunday
			Telegraph started publishing them on a weekly basis.
		</para>
		<para>
			Paint by numbers puzzles were implemented by 1995 on hand held electronic
			toys such as Game Boy and on other plastic puzzle toys. Nintendo
			picked
			up on this puzzle fad and released two "Picross" (Picture Crossword)
			titles for the Game Boy and nine for the Super Famicom in Japan. Only
			one of these, Mario's Picross for the Game Boy, was released outside
			of
			Japan."
		</para>

	</blockquote>
  	
	<figure xml:id="fig.nono_example">
		<title>Solved nonogramm</title>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="./images/nono_example.png" scalefit="1"
					width="100%" contentdepth="100%" />
			</imageobject>
			<textobject>
				<phrase>
				</phrase>
			</textobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</figure>

	<para>
		<xref linkend="fig.nono_example" /> shows a solved nonogram puzzle.
		In the first row to blocks with two and six colored fields are shown.
		Directly left of this row this two numbers are shown to help solve the
		nonogram. 
	</para>

	<para>
		The exact position of the two blocks can not be got from the row and 
		column captions. They could also be at the outer margin of the board.
		By combining the horizontal and vertical information the solution for
		the puzzle can be found. So the nonograms can be solved step-by-step.
	</para>

	<para>
		In FreeNono fields can be colored by left mouse click. To mark fields
		that should not be colored you can use the right mouse button. FreeNono
		can also be played with the keyboard. The control keys can be set in
		the options dialog.
	</para>
	
</chapter>
